Diamant, Alfred mss., 1917-2012 LMC 2822
Lilly Library
Diamant, Alfred mss.
1917-2012
Lilly Library
Diamant, Alfred, 1917-2012
Diamant, Ann Redmon, 1913-2003
LMC 2822
4 Boxes
The Diamant, Alfred mss., 1917-2012, consists of the personal correspondence, emails, school records, military papers, birth and marriage certificates, and family trees of Alfred Diamant. It also includes various drafts and pre-publication copies of his and his wife's co-authored memoir Worlds Apart, Worlds United: A European-American Story.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2014
Biographical Note
Alfred Diamant (1917-2012) was a professor at Indiana University from 1967-1988, serving as Chair of Political Science and West European Studies. He was born in Vienna, Austria on September 25 to a Slovakian Jewish merchant family and witnessed the rise of Nazism growing up. Unable to pursue a degree in history and teach due to Nazi legislation, Diamant initially entered the family textile business. After Kristallnacht in 1938 however, he sought ways to immigrate to the United States and finally succeeded in 1940. Diamant joined the military immediately after Pearl Harbor, fought and was wounded during the Allied invasion of Normandy on June 6th, 1944. During the war, he also gained his citizenship and married his wife, Ann.
After World War II, Diamant received his A.B. from Indiana University in 1947 and his PhD from Yale in 1957. He went on to teach and conduct research at the University of Florida (1950-1960), Haverford College (1960-1967), returning to Indiana University until his retirement (1967-1988). He also founded the Faculty Research Seminars in Comparative Administration and Development as well as participating in an eight year study on administration development with the Ford Foundation. Diamant devoted his professional academic career to studying political theory and comparative public administration, striving to answer the fundamental question of how social relationships affect the decisions and actions of political and social organizations and institutions.
Scope and Content Note
The Diamant, Alfred mss., 1917-2012, consists of the personal correspondence, emails, school records, military papers, birth and marriage certificates, and family trees of Alfred Diamant. It also includes various drafts and pre-publication copies of his and his wife's co-authored memoir Worlds Apart, Worlds United: A European-American Story. Although he is best known for his academic contributions, Diamant mss. reflects Diamant's personal life more than his academic career.
The Biographical series includes information on Diamant's personal life. Records from his life in Vienna, as well as his military and school records are included.
The Correspondence series includes the following subseries: correspondence with his daughter Alice, correspondence with his mother Julia, correspondence concerning his immigration to the United States, personal correspondence, and correspondence concerning his publications.
Writings includes manuscripts and galley proofs for Diamant's publications, especially his memoir Worlds Apart, Worlds United: A European-American Story which he wrote with his wife Ann Redmon Diamant.
A subseries of family trees tracing Diamant's lineage completes the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Biographical; II. Correspondence; III. Writings.
Related Material
The Alfred Diamant papers, 1950-2010, bulk 1960-1996, are located at the University Archives, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
College teachers; Political scientists--United States; Diamant, Ann Redmon, 1913-2003
- Biographical, 1917-2006
  - General Documents (Box 1)
    - 1917-2006, undated (Box 1)
  - Indiana Historical Society
    - Deed of Gift Documents, 1994-2012 (Box 1)
  - Immigration Records
    - Union Postale Universelle (Box 1)
    - Bundes-Polizeidirektion in Wien, Verkehrsamt Fuhrerschein [Federal-Police Directorate in Vienna, Office of Driver's License] (Box 1)
    - Deutsches Reich Reisepass [German Passport] (Box 1)
    - Amerikanisches Generalkonsulat Wein, Deutschland [General American Consulate of Vienna, Germany] (Box 1)
    - Kitchener Camp, Permit to Leave (Box 1)
    - Kitchener Camp, Letter of Recommendation (Box 1)
    - United States Certificate of Naturalization, Alfred Diamant (Box 1)
  - Military Records
    - 1942-1986 (Box 1)
  - School Records
    - 1930-1938 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Diamant, Alice
    - 2006 (Box 1)
    - 2007 (Box 1)
    - 2008 (Box 1)
    - 2009 (Box 1)
    - 2010 (Box 1)
    - 2012 (Box 1)
  - Diamant, Julia
    - 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Immigration, 1938-1939
    - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Personal, 1939-1941
    - 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Original Manuscript (Box 1)
      - Editor's Remarks (Box 1)
      - Publishers/Correspondence (Box 1)
    - May 2003 Manuscript (Box 1)
      - Double Spaced Version (Box 1)
    - Sep. 2005 Manuscript (Box 1)
    - Prepublication Manuscript (Box 1)
      - March 2007, Copy 2 (Box 1)
    - First Galley Proofs (Box 1)
      - August 2009 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Publishing Guide (Box 1)
  - Original Manuscript
    - Ch. 1 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 2 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 3 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 4 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 5 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 6 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 7 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 8 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 9 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 10 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 11 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 12 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 13 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 14 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 15 (Box 1)
    - Ch. 16 (Box 1)
    - Our Life Together: Ann's Story (Box 2)
    - Part I: Content Table and Introduction (Box 2)
    - Part I: Introduction (Box 2)
    - Part III: Ann Ch.'s 5-10, Handwritten (Box 2)
    - Part III: Ann Ch.'s 5-10, Typed (Box 2)
    - Part IV: Freddy Ch.'s 11-15, Typed (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Part IV: Freddy's Ch.'s 11-15, Handwritten (Box 2)
    - Part V: Conclusion, Typed Draft (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Ch. 1: Ann, Written Draft (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Ch. 2: Freddy, Typed and Written Drafts (Box 2)
    - Ch. 3: Freddy, Typed and Written Drafts (Box 2)
    - Ch. 4: Ann/Freddy, Typed and Written Drafts (Box 2)
    - Ann-MS Indiana Years, 1967-1990, Written Drafts (Box 2)
    - Chapters 1-4, Typed by Ann, Front Folder Matter (Box 2)
    - Chapters 1-4, Typed by Ann (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1990's Manuscript (Box 3)
    - Introduction and Ch. 1 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 2 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 3 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 4 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 5 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 6 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 7 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 8 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 9 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 10 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 11 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 12 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 13-14 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 15 (Box 3)
    - Ch. 16 (Box 3)
  - May 2003 Manuscript
    - Single Spaced Version (Box 3)
    - Double Spaced Version (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Sep. 2005 Manuscript
    - Sep. 2005 Manuscript (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Front Pocket Matter (Box 3)
    - Back Pocket Matter (Box 3)
  - Prepublication Manuscript, Mar. 2007 (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - Copy 1 (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - Copy 2 (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - Copy 3 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - First Galley Proofs, August 2009 (Box 3)
    - First Galley Proofs, August 2009 (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Front Pocket Matter (Box 3)
    - Back Pocket Matter (Box 3)
  - 11.5" x 17.5" Family Trees (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 1. Descendants of Tunis Quick & Susannah Records (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 2. Descendants of James Hoagland Quick & Martha Ellen Vanskike (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 3. Vanskike (Van Schoyk) Family Tree (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 4. Everson Family Tree (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 5. Descendants of George Washington Quick & Anna Mae Everson (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 6. Descendants of Mary Louetta Quick & Carl Hugh Redmon (1 of 6) (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 7. Descendants of Mary Louetta Quick & Carl Hugh Redmon (2 of 6) (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 8. Descendants of Mary Louetta Quick & Carl Hugh Redmon (3 of 6) (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 9. Descendants of Mary Louetta Quick & Carl Hugh Redmon (4 of 6) (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 10. Descendants of Mary Louetta Quick & Carl Hugh Redmon (5 of 6) (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 11. Descendants of Mary Louetta Quick & Carl Hugh Redmon (6 of 6) (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 12. Descendants of Joesph Christopher Redmond & Mary Elizabeth King (Box 4 (Oversize))
    - 13. King Family Tree (1 of 2) (Box 4 (Oversize))